Finding Aid for Kathy and Angelos Constantinides papers, 1899-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kathy and Angelos Constantinides papers 1889-2012
Constantinides, Kathy, 1936-
1.1 linear feet
2012044 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Angelos and Kathy Constantinides (donor no. 10541 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions, 2011 and May 2013.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Kathy Bakalis was born in Detroit, Michigan in 1936. Her parents had immigrated from Greece in 1927. She graduated from Lincoln High School in 1954 and Wayne State University in 1958. In December of that same year she married Angelos Constantinides. With her husband, Kathy shared many community and volunteer activities. In the 1970s, she worked on the Equal Rights Amendment campaign. She was active in other gender and women's issues, and was, in addition, a recognized artist.
Angelos Constantinides was born August 15, 1927 in Port Said, Egypt. As citizens of Greece, his parents registered his birth with the Greek Consulate. He graduated from the Greek Community High School in Port Said in 1944. He immigrated to the United States in 1947. He served in the Korean War following which he attended and graduated from Wayne University in Detroit in 1955. He graduated from the Chicago College of Osteopathy in June 1959 and established a general practice in Romulus, Michigan (1960-1977). From 1977 to 1988, he was occupational physician with the Ford Motor Company in Dearborn. He retired in 1988.
The Kathy and Angelos Constantinides collection consists of family materials, files relating to Kathy Constantinides's involvement in women's and civil rights issues, documents from the education and career of Angelos Constantinides, and files from their shared involvement in the American Civil Liberties Union and other organizations. Family materials include various certificates and documents from the lives of George and Eleni Constantinides (Angelos's parents) and Pete and Hrissi Bakalis (Kathy's parents). Of note is The Autobiography of Pete John Bakalis translated and edited by Kathy. The papers of Kathy (Bakalis) Constantinides includes her various writings -- an autobiography, a family history, as well as her extensive correspondence to newspaper editors and organizations on gender and women's rights issues. The Angelos Constantinides papers documents his education and his service during the Korean War.
Subjects:
Bakalis, Pete.; Bakalis, Hrissi.; Constantinides, Angelos.; Constantinides, Eleni.; Constantinides, George.; Constantinides, Kathy, 1936-; Greek Americans--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.
Contributors:
Constantinides, Angelos.
- George and Eleni Constantinides
  - Early documents: dowry agreement, 1889 and cantina permit, 1900 (Box 1)
  - Binder of various legal documents: birth certificate, passport, etc. (Box 2)
- Pete and Hrissi Bakalis
  - The Autobiography of Pete John Bakalis (Panayiotis Ioannou Bakalis) translated by Angelos and Kathy (Bakalis) Constantinides (1994) (Box 2)
    (also include photocopy of the original text in Greek; the autobiography was started in 1982)
  - Text of book "Apolloniada," the story of Pete and Hrissi Bakalis's village (Box 2)
    (also include map made by Kathy Constantinides of this village)
  - Ellis Island material (Box 2)
  - Various documents (Box 2)
- Kathy (Bakalis) Constantinides
  - Autobiography entitled "Remembering" (Box 2)
  - Family history entitled Hrissi (1987) (Box 2)
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 2)
  - Van Dyke, Michigan Public Schools teaching documents (Box 2)
  - Wayne State University: transcript, commencement program, admission to WSU Graduate School (Box 2)
  - Eastern Michigan University: graduate teaching assistant contract, gradation program, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Eastern Michigan University: art dept. grades (Box 2)
  - Grade school and high school certificates; also graduation diploma and program (Box 2)
  - Letters to the editor and to organizations on topics of women's rights and civil liberties, 1979-2010
    - Gender neutral language usage (Box 2)
    - Art censorship (Box 2)
    - Gender and women's issues (Box 2)
    - Women's Rights National Historical Park (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Noise complaints (Box 2)
    - Reproductive rights and abortion (Box 2)
    - Letters used in book "Letters: Liberty Circumscribed" (Box 2)
  - Clergy sexual misconduct (Box 2)
  - Handbook by KC entitled Challenging Professional Sexual Exploitation (1993) (Box 2)
  - Church baptismal certificate (Box 1)
  - Lincoln High School graduation class photo (Box 1)
- Angelos Constantinides
  - Autobiography (Box 2)
  - Certificate from Medical Field Service School (Box 2)
  - Various certificates (Box 2)
  - Certificate of recognition and related correspondence, U.S. Army Cold War Recognition Office (Box 2)
  - Wayne State University transcript; also curriculum vitae (Box 2)
  - Passport (Box 2)
  - Chicago College of Osteopathy class of 1959 class photo (Box 1)
  - Various professional certificates (Box 1)
  - Grade school and high school diplomas (Box 1)
- Shared activities
  - Genealogy (Box 2)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (regarding their gift to the ACLU) (Box 2)
  - Neighbors, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Letters from relatives in Greece (Box 2)
    (in Greek, with translations)
  - Various documents: certificates, etc. (Box 2)
- Digital Files
  - DVD-R files of the materials from the collection, 2 DVD-Rs (Box 2)
Related Material
Additional papers of Kathy Constantinides are available at the Labadie Collection, Hatcher Library, University of Michigan.